兩千年前  戰國時期  中國共分為七個國家
Two thousand years ago... during the Warring States period, China was divided into seven Kingdoms.
多年來  七國之間為了爭權奪霸  戰亂連連  各國百姓苦不堪言
For years they battled for supremacy while the people suffered.
而在征伐諸國  試圖一統天下的七國君王中  秦王是最暴虐無情的一個
The King of Qin was the most ruthless in his efforts to conquer the land and unify all under heaven.
他被其他六國視為共同的威脅
He was regarded as a common threat by the other six Kingdoms.
中國歷代編年史中記載了許多刺殺君王的史實
The annals of Chinese history are abound with tales of the assassins sent to kill the great King.
這是其中的一個傳奇故事
This is one of those legends...
我  自幼便為孤兒
I was orphaned at an early age.
也沒有名字  人稱無名
I had no name, so people called me Nameless.
人若無名  便可專心練劍
Being a nobody, I studied swordsmanship.
我花十年
After 10 years of practice,
練成一種獨特劍法
I acquired a unique skill.
秦王緊急召見我
The King of Qin has summoned me.
是因為我已辦成一件驚動秦國的大事
My deeds have astonished the Kingdom.
臣奉我王之命
By order of his Majesty,
接壯士星夜兼程趕回  拜見丞相
we have brought the mighty warrior.
長空  飛雪  殘劍
Sky, Flying Snow and Broken Sword,
這三名趙國刺客
the three assassins from Zhao
十年來謀刺我王
have sought his Majesty's life. For 10 years
令我王一日不得安睡
his Majesty has known no peace.
怎料今日
To the astonishment of all
卻被我大秦壯士一舉擊破
a mighty warrior of Qin has smashed them.
從此我王可以高枕無憂了
His Majesty can finally sleep at night!
臣等恭賀我王
We rejoice for our King!
天降壯士
This warrior sent from heaven
剪除刺客
has exterminated the assassins.
大王令  召壯士
Summon the warrior!
上殿拜見大王  需在百步之外
Remain 100 paces from his Majesty.
否則格殺勿論  壯士切記
Or you will be executed. Never forget that.
十年來  從未有人上殿近寡人百步
No one is allowed within 100 paces of me.
可知為何
Do you know why?
刺客猖獗
To guard against assassins.
不錯  刺客一日不除  我難解甲冑
Yes. That's why I am confined in this armor.
如今你替寡人除此大害
You have removed a great peril for me.
要何封賞
How should I reward you?
為秦殺賊  不求封賞
My service was for Qin, not for a reward.
大秦治下  必有封賞
Achievements must be rewarded.
長空銀槍
Sky's silver spear...
曾傷我大秦多少壯士
wounded many of my brave warriors.
宣我法令
Announce my edict!
大王法令
By order of his Majesty,
有破刺客長空者  賞千金  封千戶侯
he who kills Sky will receive gold and land
上殿二十步
and be allowed to drink
與王對飲
within 20 paces of his Majesty.
據寡人接報  你是我秦國人
I am informed you're a citizen of Qin.
臣  狼孟縣亭長無名
I am a Prefect from Leng Meng County.
區區亭長  轄區不過十里
A County Prefect over 10 square miles!
是我大秦國最小的官吏
Surely the lowest-ranking official in Qin
有何本事  能破趙國的三大刺客
how did you defeat such opponents?
各個擊破
I took them on one by one.
仔細講來
Tell me the details.
大王可知
Does Your Majesty know
殘劍  飛雪為一對情侶
Flying Snow and Broken Sword were lovers?
寡人知道
Yes, I do.
大王可曾聽說  他們三年無話
And that they hadn't spoken for three years?
三年無話  為何
For three years? Why?
皆因飛雪與長空曾有一夜之情
Flying Snow had an affair with Sky.
使殘劍耿耿於懷
Broken Sword never forgave her.
寡人怎麼未曾聽說呀
Why haven't I heard this before?
臣想方設法  才獲此秘情
I went to great lengths to uncover it.
所以分化殘劍飛雪
To divide Flying Snow and Broken Sword.
必先取長空
I first needed to eliminate Sky.
你的做法  寡人猜到一二了
I have an idea of what you planned.
大王賢明
Your Majesty is wise.
對長空  你以何為戰
What did you use to defeat Sky?
劍
The sword.
在狼孟縣  臣掌管緝捕盜賊
I must arrest criminals in my county.
六月初五
On the fifth day of the sixth month.
長空在一家棋館內現身
Sky attended a chess house.
臣打聽到
I had learnt he enjoyed playing chess
他常來此地下棋聽琴
and listening to music there.
秦宮七大高手
So, the seven masters of Qin Palace.
跟你多日  拿你歸案
We are here to arrest you!
亮出銀槍  驗明正身
Identify yourself by showing your spear.
慢
Halt!
小小亭長  有何貴幹
What can a minor official do?
此地歸我轄管
This is my territory.
如何
So?
你乃大王通緝的要犯
You are on the King's most wanted list.
我當拿你歸案
I am placing you under arrest.
老先生  請再撫一曲
Old man, please play one more tune.
武功琴韻雖不相同
Martial arts and music are different,
但原理相通
but they share the same principle.
都講求大音希聲之境界
Both stress attaining a supreme state.
臣和長空面對面站著  有半個時辰
Sky and I faced each other for a long time.
雖然誰也沒動
Neither of us moved.
但決鬥已經在彼此的意念中繼續展開
We fought the battle in our minds.
好快的劍
How swift thy sword!
寡人自恃對秦國的一草一木瞭如指掌
I thought I knew everything about my Kingdom.
卻不知狼孟縣內
I didn't know that Leng Meng County
居然有你這樣的人才
held a talent like yours.
殘劍
Broken Sword.
飛雪
Flying Snow.
大王法令
By order of his Majesty!
刺客殘劍  刺客飛雪
Flying Snow and Broken Sword
素來聯手行刺
have teamed up for assassination,
有誅殺二人中任何一人者
he who kills either of them
賞萬金  封五千戶侯
will receive gold and land
上殿十步
and be allowed to drink
與王對飲
within 10 paces of his Majesty.
三年前
Three years ago, Flying Snow
雙劍聯手攻入宮中
stormed the palace with Broken Sword.
三千鐵甲竟不能擋
3000 elite troops couldn't stop them.
從此寡人將這大殿清掃一空
I've since emptied the palace,
使刺客無法藏身
so assassins cannot hide.
你的劍竟能快過此二人
Was your sword swifter than theirs combined?
不能
No.
那你如何取勝
How did you do it, then?
臣喬裝成趙人
Disguised as a citizen of Zhao.
去趙國尋找殘劍飛雪
I sought them in the Kingdom of Zhao.
臣探聽到
I learned they were hiding.
兩人化名高山  流水
In a calligraphy school.
藏身於趙國陘城一家書館
Under the names Highcliff and Springbrook.
那天風聞
Rumor had it
大王大軍將要攻趙
the Qin army would attack that day.
陘城中百姓已逃散一空
Most of the townspeople had fled.
只餘下書館弟子
Only the school's students remained.
客人為何此時前來
Why have you come at such a time?
你是何人
Who are you?
在下趙國易縣人
I'm from Yi County in the Kingdom of Zhao.
先父臨終留下遺願
My father's dying wish
求貴館一副墨寶
was for one of your scrolls.
今日  我書館已是最後一日了
I fear this may be our school's last day.
客人求何人之字
Which calligrapher do you seek?
求高山先生
I respectfully request Master Highcliff.
高山先生  便是殘劍
Highcliff was Broken Sword
傳說他由書法中悟出
Legend said his skill as a swordsman
一套劍法  威力無比
was rooted in his calligraphy.
臣對此頗有顧慮
So I had my concerns.
所以臣想先看殘劍的書法
I needed to find out if it was true.
求何字
What do you want written?
劍
"Sword."
客人是愛劍之人
You are fond of the sword?
在下只是完成先父的遺願
It was my father's dying wish.
幾尺
What size scroll?
八尺
Eight feet.
八尺劍字  需要硃砂
For that size I will need red ink.
有客人求字
My master has asked me
主人特向小姐借硃砂一用
to borrow some red ink.
主人向小姐借硃砂
My master wants to borrow some red ink.
不知小姐聽清了沒有
Did you hear me, Master Springbrook?
主人向小姐借硃砂
Master Highcliff wants to borrow red ink.
叫他自己過來
Tell him to come himself.
弟子來借硃砂
Could I have some red ink?
臣求的劍字  還沒有寫成
The character "sword" was still being written
大王攻趙的軍隊
when Your Majesty's troops
此時已到陘城城外了
arrived at the city gates.
射
Draw!
大王軍隊  之所以百戰百勝
Your Majesty's army is invincible,
除能征善戰外
not only because it is brave,
便在於弓強箭快
but also because of its archery
六國的箭都不及秦箭射得遠
with a greater range than any other army.
大王軍隊每到一處  必例行放箭
The Qin archers are like artillery
試探敵情  威懾四方
intimidating the enemy.
風  風  風
Hail! hail! hail!
你們記住
Please remember
秦國的箭再強
their arrows might destroy our town
可以破我們的城  滅我們的國
and topple our Kingdom,
可亡不了趙國的字
but they can never obliterate our culture.
今日
Today,
你們要學到趙國文字的精義
you will learn the essence of our culture.
風  風  風
Hail! hail! hail!
那些趙人  當真不動
Those Zhao people didn't flee?
趙國書法  剛烈過人
They drew strength from their calligraphy.
你所求劍字  有何難寫
What was so difficult about "sword"?
劍的寫法  通常有一十九種
There are 19 different ways to write it.
臣向殘劍所求
I asked Broken Sword
是除去十九種變化的第二十種
for a 20th way.
書法劍術
Both calligraphy and swordplay
都靠手腕之力與胸中之氣
rely on one's strength and spirit.
這第二十種
The 20th style would reveal
便有他劍術的精妙藏於字中
the essence of his swordsmanship.
一個字  竟有十九種寫法
How odd to write it in 19 ways.
又互不相認
It makes the written language
極為不便
impossible to comprehend.
等寡人滅了六國之後
Once I've conquered the six Kingdoms
再滅其它諸國
and all the northern tribes,
必將這些雜七雜八的文字
I will eradicate this problem,
統統廢掉
by mandating one style of writing.
只留一種  豈不痛快
Wouldn't that be ideal?
大王不是只滅六國嗎
Your Majesty won't stop at the six Kingdoms?
六國算什麼
The six Kingdoms are nothing!
寡人要率大秦的鐵騎
I will lead my army to conquer vast lands
打下一個大大的疆土
and establish a great empire.
風  風  風
Hail! hail! hail!
是流水先生
Master Springbrook.
為何離開
Why are you going outside?
我去擋箭
To fend off the arrows.
不用你去  退下
You aren't needed. Stay inside.
秦軍箭陣  聞名天下
The Qin archers are powerful.
流水先生未必能擋
You alone may not stop them.
風  風  風
Hail! hail! hail!
好身手
You are good.
流水先生更是好身手
You are even better.
你不為求字而來
You didn't come here for calligraphy.
你是誰
Who are you?
在下特地送一件東西請先生過目
I've travelled here to deliver an item.
子夜藏書閣
Please meet me in the library at midnight.
好字
Great calligraphy.
好劍法
Great swordplay.
先生並未看我出劍
You didn't even see my swordplay.
若無你的劍  也無此字
I couldn't have written without it.
今夜子時
At midnight
請先生去藏書閣看一件東西
meet me in the library.
大王幾十萬大軍
Several hundred thousand Qin troops
當晚在山下安營紮寨準備攻趙
were readying for the next onslaught.
臣則連夜悟字
I studied the character all night,
想找出殘劍劍法之走勢
trying to unlock the secret of his skills.
你說這字中有劍法
It would reveal his swordsmanship?
可在寡人看來  這只是普通之字
But it's just an ordinary word.
書法劍術  境界相通
Calligraphy and swordplay are similar
奧妙全靠領悟
One must comprehend their true essence.
你領悟到了
Did you discover it?
尚未悟透
It eluded me.
悟不透  你如何挑戰他們
So how did you challenge them?
臣探之  殘劍與飛雪雖三年無話
Although they hadn't spoken in three years They spied on each other.
但每晚子時
At midnight
殘劍都會窺看飛雪
Broken Sword would peek into Flying Snow's room.
而到了丑時
At 2 o'clock in the morning,
飛雪同樣悄悄窺視殘劍
she would spy on Broken Sword.
二人行為如此怪異
What strange behaviour.
是  臣也驚訝二人關係如此奇怪
I was surprised too.
特地送去銀槍  以求利用
So I used Sky's silver spear to get to them.
長空是敗在你的劍下
Sky died by your sword?
是
Yes.
你是何人  為何來此
Who are you? Why are you here?
在下實為秦人
I'm from the Kingdom of Qin.
替長空帶來一句話
I have a message from Sky.
講
Go on.
長空說
he said he had lived a life
他此生縱橫江湖  無牽無掛
without responsibilities or commitments,
唯有一人常留心中
he cared for only one person.
誰
Who?
飛雪
Flying Snow.
長空說  飛雪定會替他報仇
Sky was certain she'd avenge his death.
若要同在下一戰  明日秦軍大營
To fight, meet me at the Qin camp.
你走
You can leave now.
走吧
Go!
我知道你看見了
I know you saw us!
我告訴你
Let me tell you,
我跟她這樣已經三年了
we've been together for three years.
我故意讓你看見的
I let you see us on purpose!
我心裏根本沒有你
I no longer care about you at all!
你我都很蠢
We were both very foolish.
我只是要你對我好一點
I just wanted you to care about me.
我不跟你動手
I'm not going to fight you.
走
Go away!
我要殺了你  為主人報仇
I will kill you in honor of my master!
你既然找死  我成全你
You ask to die. I will help you.
你笑什麼
Why do you laugh?
我笑你昨晚做了蠢事
What you did last night was stupid.
飛雪與臣決戰時
My plan proved successful.
因臣的計謀已然奏效
When Flying Snow was fighting me,
所以她氣血攻心  方寸大亂
she was disturbed and disoriented.
臣嬴得絲毫不費力氣
I defeated her easily.
想不到殘劍飛雪
I never imagined supreme warriors
竟如此怪異
like Broken Sword and Flying Snow
也會被情所困
allowing their emotions to be a liability.
寡人聽來  此戰你嬴在二人不和上
It sounds as if you did divide them.
是
Yes.
之所以不和
In that case, they must have been
二人必是心胸狹小之輩
petty and narrow-minded.
是
True.
你講的故事倒也合情合理
Your story sounds logical.
可寡人看來
But,
你把一個人想簡單了
you have underestimated one person.
誰
Who?
我
Me.
你想不想知  寡人對他們印象如何
Would you like my impression of them?
三年前  寡人曾與他們有過一戰
Three years ago they stormed the palace.
在寡人看來
I was impressed
這二人光明磊落氣度不凡
by their valor and dignity.
絕非小人之輩
Their character could not be petty.
所以  一夜之情是假
So Flying Snow's affair with Sky is a lie.
反目成仇是假
Their betrayal of one another is a lie.
你所講故事更是假
The story you just told is a lie!
只有一件事是真
Except for one thing,
長空認識你們其中一人
Sky did know one of you.
誰
Who?
你
You.
寡人猜測  你與長空早就相識
I surmise you two were old friends.
長空敗給你  只有一個理由
And Sky's defeat has only one explanation.
什麼理由
What's that?
故意求敗
He permitted it.
你與長空為行刺寡人  暗自串通
To kill me, the two of you formed a pact,
引我秦宮高手在一旁觀看作證
using my men as witnesses.
布此圈套  並不困難
That was not hard to arrange.
難在長空竟能將莫大信任
The hardest part was to persuade Sky
托付給你
to put his life in your hands.
你的劍雖快  未必能勝得了長空
You were not fast enough to defeat Sky,
但長空卻自願倒在你的劍下
he died willingly under your sword.
如此胸懷  令人嘆服
Such devotion deserves true respect.
所以長空是你的
He was the first to sacrifice himself
第一位捐助者
for your mission.
寡人在想  長空心高氣傲
Sky was proud,
自認天下無敵
he saw himself as an unrivalled fighter.
他何以認定  他做不到的事情
What convinced him you could succeed
唯你能成功
where he had failed?
莫非你專為行刺  而十年練劍
You have trained, perhaps for 10 years
你的劍術中藏有一式
with one goal, my assassination.
威力巨大  無人能比
You have a great skill that few can counter.
得到長空  你已能上殿二十步
Killing Sky got you within 20 paces of me.
為何還尋找殘劍  飛雪
So why seek out Broken Sword and Flying Snow?
寡人猜想  你所練行刺劍法
I surmise that your skill
一定以十步為距
requires you to come within 10 paces.
所以  你還需利用寡人的懸賞令
You needed a second sacrifice
尋找第二名捐助者
to claim another reward
再進十步
to bring you within 10 paces.
寡人以為  殘劍飛雪
Although Broken Sword and Flying Snow
雖與長空素昧平生
had never met Sky,
但立即明白了
they instantly understood
長空故意求敗的理由
the reason for his defeat.
此處距書簡幾步
How far am I from the bookshelves?
大約十步
About 10 paces.
好  就是十步
10 paces is fine.
在下只需一人相助
I need one of you to help me.
兩位請自行決定
Please decide between yourselves.
明晨  秦軍大營
Meet me at the Qin camp tomorrow morning.
好快的劍
How swift thy sword!
是
True.
長空是當今大俠
Sky was a superior warrior,
竟能將性命交與此人
he willingly gave his life to this man,
所以他能夠刺秦
he can kill the King.
我們要去
We must proceed.
去  就是死
That means we will die.
死就一起死
Then we die together.
我比你晚了一步
You were one step ahead of me.
我怕把你傷得太重了
Did I hurt you too much?
應該是我去
I should be the one who fights him.
我要你活下去
I want you to live.
你死了  我怎麼活
If you died, how could I live?
你答應我  要好好的活
You will live on, promise me.
你說啊
Say it!
好
All right.
如月快要到了
Moon is on her way,
我先走了
I had better go.
在下狼孟縣亭長無名
I am Nameless, Prefect of Leng Meng County.
捉拿趙國刺客到此  懇請單獨一戰
Please allow me to fight this assassin.
此人是大王通緝的要犯
She is on his Majesty's most wanted list.
既在此地現身  我當就地擒拿
Now she's here, I will arrest her.
在下與刺客曾有言在先
The assassin and I have an agreement
要單獨決一勝負
to fight one on one.
如在下不能取勝
Should I be unable to defeat her,
再有勞將軍援手相助
please apprehend her.
望將軍恩准
Your permission is sought.
出你的劍
Draw your sword!
風  風  風
Hail! hail! hail!
快動手
Make your move!
風  風  風
Hail! hail! hail!
為刺秦我死而無憾
I die willingly.
請動手吧
Make your move.
大風  大風  大風
Hail! hail! hail!
好快的劍
How swift thy sword!
你已拿了飛雪劍  為何還來
What are you here for?
你曾說過一句話
For what you once said.
是  誰傷飛雪  我必出劍
"I will fight the one who harms Flying Snow."
請出劍
Please draw your sword.
多謝
Thank you.
寡人以為  你與殘劍之間也曾有一戰
I believe you and Broken Sword also fought,
你們二人的交手絕非生死之戰
but rather it was.
而是以此種方式祭奠飛雪
A fight to honor Flying Snow.
主人交你此劍
My master wishes you to have his sword.
為何交劍
Why?
殘劍飛雪  生死相守
He and she are bound in life and death.
人不離人  劍不離劍
They will never part, nor will their swords.
主人給你此劍
It is his dying wish
助你一同刺秦
that you take his sword for your mission.
長空  飛雪  殘劍
Sky, Flying Snow and Broken Sword
分別以不同方式捐出自己
sacrificed themselves,
助你上殿十步來刺寡人
so you can be within 10 paces of me.
此三人能把生命托付給你
All three gave you their lives.
人生知己  也莫過於此了
The best of friends could not give more.
所以  你才是
Therefore you are
最危險的刺客
the most dangerous assassin of all.
大王何以識破
How did you uncover my plan?
寡人面前的燭火
The flames of these candles
感到了你的殺氣
are disturbed by your murderous intent.
他們三人  還有你
All of you
捨身取義
are willing to die for a cause.
寡人自愧不如
I'm ashamed to say I am not that committed.
大王畢竟識破了
Your Majesty has seen through our plan.
寡人也是剛剛識破
If I had realised this sooner,
否則怎會容你近我十步
I wouldn't have allowed you so close
秦人不會刺我
A citizen of Qin would not do this.
你到底是誰
Who are you?
臣實為趙人
A man of Zhao.
臣家人被秦軍所殺
Your Qin soldiers killed my family,
自幼流落在秦
I wandered into Qin
被秦人收養
and was adopted.
十年前知道身世
I discovered my real identity 10 years ago
便決心行刺
and set my heart on this plan.
為趙而來
You've come to avenge Zhao.
寡人明白了
I see.
寡人想知道
I would like to know
你練的快劍名稱
if your special skill has a name.
如大王所猜
As Your Majesty guessed,
藏有一式
there is only one crucial move.
哪一式
What is that?
十步一殺
"Death within 10 Paces."
十步一殺  好名字
"Death within 10 Paces." A good name!
寡人的衛士
All my guards are 100 paces away
均在殿外的百步之遙
outside the palace.
而你近寡人已十步
You are within 10 paces.
看來
It would seem
寡人今日是難逃此劫
that today I am doomed.
你的殺氣在亂
But I sense your hesitation.
大王見識過人
Your Majesty is perceptive.
可是
However,
大王也把一個人想簡單了
you too have underestimated someone.
誰
Who?
殘劍
Broken Sword.
臣要向他們證明
I needed to prove to them
臣的劍不僅快  且精準無誤
that my sword was fast and accurate.
在下所練快劍
Within 10 paces,
十步之內  絕無偏差
my sword strikes with surgical precision.
若從膈腧穴入  步廊穴出
If it enters at precise pressure points,
便能不傷臟器  令人傷而不死
it will not cause any fatal injury.
只求兩位中任何一位
If one of you would take a blow
能當眾受我一劍  騙過秦王耳目
before witnesses, we can fool the King.
當眾受你一劍  豈是兒戲
Such a blow is hardly child's play.
長空現在如何
How is Sky now?
現已無妨
Fully recovered.
難得他對你的劍法如此信任
His trust in your sword was extraordinary.
秦王防範嚴密  無法接近
The King's security is impenetrable.
只能如此
There was no other way.
那些秦宮衛士  不值一提
His lmperial Guards were useless.
其實三年前秦王就該死了
He should have died three years ago.
何以失手
What went wrong?
是我放棄了
I abandoned the plan.
秦王不能殺
The King must not be killed.
殘劍這樣講
He said that?
是
Yes.
為何
Why?
臣也這樣問他
I also asked him.
他如何作答
What did he say?
當日殘劍不願細說
He would not explain that day.
長空  飛雪  殘劍
Broken Sword is the strongest of the three,
三人中唯有殘劍的劍法與臣不相上下
he and I are probably equal in skills.
因此殘劍後來對臣說的話
What he told me later
使臣頗有顧慮
greatly unsettled me.
有我在
While I'm alive,
便要阻止你刺秦
I'll stop you assassinating the King.
我願助你
I will help you.
三年前  有人錯失良機
He let the opportunity go by.
這次  一定要成功
This time, we must succeed.
明早  秦軍大營見
See you tomorrow at the Qin camp.
你幫我一件事
Please do me a favor.
出劍助我
Help me fight Broken Sword!
主人
Master!
還不出劍
What are you waiting for?
臣雖答應飛雪出劍相助
Although I had agreed to help her
但總以為有失正大光明
attack from behind is dishonorable,
故遲遲不能出手
so I couldn't draw my sword.
然而臣與飛雪都明白
But we both knew
如不阻擋殘劍
if we did not stop Broken Sword,
便絕無成功可能
we would never succeed.
如月住手
Moon, don't!
你不是他對手  住手吧
You're no match for him. Stop.
我知道你會這樣做
I knew this would happen.
這樣你就不能攔我了
You can't stop me now.
就算傷我  我還會阻攔
Even wounded, I will still stop you.
那我會殺了你
Then I will kill you!
我怕把他傷得太重了
Did I hurt him too much?
有小姐的創傷藥
Your special medicine
一日後應無大礙
should heal his wounds in a day.
藥送了嗎
have you delivered it?
是我親手替先生敷上的
I tended to the wound myself.
今天戰後  你捧飛雪劍
After the battle, take my sword
跟來人進秦宮
and follow Nameless to see the King.
是
Yes.
秦國不會為難你這個下人
They won't treat a servant harshly.
如刺秦成功
If the assassination succeeds,
打紅旗回來
wave a red flag on your return.
失敗了  黃旗
If it fails, a yellow one.
小姐此戰若有不幸
If something happens to you,
報信何用
any message will be useless.
那我在天之靈
I will smile from heaven
見紅旗也會含笑
if I see a red flag.
飛雪如何
How is Flying Snow?
正在養息
She is resting.
我是背著她而來
She doesn't know I've come.
你曾說過  有你在便會阻擋
You said you'd stop me.
請你放棄刺秦
Please abandon the mission.
你可知我是趙人
You know I am a man of Zhao.
我也是
So am I.
秦國是否要滅趙
Doesn't Qin want to conquer Zhao?
是
Yes.
秦王是否趙國的敵人
Isn't the King the enemy of Zhao?
是
Yes.
那你在替誰說話
Who are you trying to defend?
你如何配做趙人
You call yourself a man of Zhao?
你的話  飛雪也曾經這樣問我
Flying Snow has asked me that too.
那年我浪跡江湖
When we first met,
碰到飛雪
I was living a carefree life.
那一戰  使我愛上飛雪
I fell in love with her after our first fight.
飛雪是趙國大將趙震之女
She's the daughter of a Zhao general
秦趙之戰中  趙震身亡
who died in battle against Qin.
傳下飛雪劍給她
She inherited his sword.
我知道飛雪立志刺秦
I knew she would avenge her father.
為父報仇  便有心幫她
I promised to help her.
書法劍術  同源同理
Calligraphy and swordplay
我和飛雪每日習字
share the same principles.
想從書法中悟出一套劍法
We did calligraphy to inspire our swordplay
增進功力
and to heighten our powers.
飛雪知道  我從小浪跡江湖
She knew I'd drifted since childhood,
四海為家  便常對我說
calling no place home.
等完成刺秦心願
Once we'd killed the King, she said
就帶我回她的家  她說
she would take me to her home.
那裏沒有劍  也沒有劍客
There'd be no more swordsmen,
只有一個男人
only a man
和一個女人
and a woman.
書法之真諦  在於意境
The essence of calligraphy is from the soul.
劍法也如此
Swordsmanship is the same.
講求返樸歸真之境界
Both aspire to truth and simplicity.
於是我慢慢領悟了
Gradually I recognised a greater cause.
三年前  劍法練成
Three years ago we perfected our skills.
飛雪執意要去刺秦
Flying Snow insisted on going ahead.
我便隨飛雪一同殺入秦宮
Together, we stormed the palace.
飛雪問我  為何不殺秦王
She asked why I had abandoned the mission.
我告訴她  秦王不能殺
I told her the King must not be killed.
這是我從書法的境界中悟出的道理
That is what calligraphy taught me.
我沒有殺秦王
I didn't kill the King.
飛雪從此不再理我
After that she refused to talk to me.
請你放棄
Please abandon your plan.
不
No.
你的劍莫非只為仇恨而練
Was your sword forged in hatred?
不錯
Yes.
我的劍
For 10 years, it has never tired.
十年來不敢有一刻倦怠
I can't stop now.
你如何才肯聽
How can I dissuade you?
除非你殺了我
Only by killing me.
你一定要去
Are you that determined?
是
Yes.
那好
Allow me to convey my conviction
我送你兩個字
in three words.
字同我心
These words express my mind.
望你三思
Please consider.
如月  把劍交給無名大俠
Moon, give my sword to Master Nameless.
我跟飛雪人不離人
Flying Snow and I will never part
劍不離劍
nor will our swords.
無名大俠
Master Nameless,
如月雖身份卑微
although I am just a humble servant,
也願為主人一勸
allow me to say a few words.
如月身為丫環  八歲跟了主人
I've been with my master since I was eight,
隨主人研習武藝
he taught me martial arts,
更懂得做人的道理
and how to be a decent person.
主人做的事
Whatever my master does
一定不會錯
is for a good reason.
主人給你寫的字
The words he has given you
一定有道理
carry a deep meaning.
如月只能為主人做最後一件事了
This will be the last thing I can do for my master.
無名大俠  請你記住主人這兩個字
Master Nameless, please take his advice.
為何如此
Why did you want to do that?
我聽主人講過一個故事
I wanted to follow the example of my master,
如月願效仿古人  以死相勸
and to persuade you with my life.
你還小  生命可貴
You're still young. Life is precious.
死  要死得其所
If you must die you should die for a greater cause.
你去吧
Be on your way.
該記住的  我會記住
I will remember what should be remembered.
殘劍給你寫了哪兩個字
What were the words he wrote?
天下
"All under heaven."
All under heaven...
殘劍說
Broken Sword said,
七國連年混戰  百姓受苦
"The people have suffered years of warfare.
唯有大王才能停止戰亂
"Only the King of Qin can stop the chaos
一統天下
"by uniting all under heaven."
殘劍希望我  為了天下
He asked me to abandon the assassination
放棄刺殺大王
for the greater good of all.
他跟我說  一個人的痛苦
He said, one person's suffering is nothing
與天下人比  便不再是痛苦
compared to the suffering of many.
趙國與秦國的仇恨
The rivalry of Zhao and Qin is trivial
放到天下  也不再是仇恨
compared to the greater cause.
沒想到最瞭解寡人的
The person who really understands me
竟是寡人通緝的刺客
is my most feared enemy.
寡人孤獨一人
Alone, I have endured so much criticism.
忍受多少責難  多少暗算
So many attempts on my life.
無人能懂寡人之心
No one understands my intentions.
就連秦國的滿朝文武
Even my court officials
也視寡人為暴君
see me as a tyrant.
想不到殘劍
But I never imagined
與寡人素昧平生
that Broken Sword, my arch-enemy
才真正懂得寡人
would truly understand,
與寡人心意相通
and appreciate my real motives.
寡人想知道
I would like to know,
你手無寸鐵  如何刺我
how you mean to kill me without your sword?
奪劍
By capturing yours!
此劍隨寡人征戰南北
This sword has protected me
也有十年了
through all my battles.
寡人能有殘劍大俠這樣的知己
Having found a true confidant in Broken Sword,
便是死  也足矣
if I die, I am content with my life.
你就為天下
Let "All under heaven"
決定這一劍吧
guide your decision.
寡人悟到了
It's just dawned on me!
殘劍的這幅字
This scroll of Broken Sword's
根本就不含劍法招式
isn't about sword technique,
寫的是劍法的最高境界
but about swordsmanship's ultimate ideal.
劍法  其第一層境界
Swordsmanship's first achievement
講求人劍合一
is the unity of man and sword.
劍就是人  人就是劍
Once this unity is attained
手中寸草  也是利器
even a blade of grass can be a weapon.
其第二層境界
The second achievement is when
講求手中無劍  劍在心中
the sword exists in one's heart
雖赤手空拳  卻能以劍氣
when absent from one's hand One can strike an enemy at 100 paces,
殺敵於百步之外
even with bare hands.
而劍法的最高境界
Swordsmanship's ultimate achievement
則是手中無劍  心中也無劍
is the absence of the sword in both hand and heart.
是以大胸懷
The swordsman is at peace
包容一切
with the rest of the world,
那便是不殺
he vows not to kill
便是和平
and to bring peace to mankind.
大王  這一劍臣必須刺
Your Majesty, your visions have convinced me
刺了這一劍
that you are committed to the highest ideal
很多人都會死
of ultimate swordsmanship.
而大王會活著
Therefore I cannot kill you.
死去的人  請大王記住
Remember those who gave their lives
那最高的境界
for the highest ideal: peace.
無名已近秦王十步
No more killing Nameless went within 10 paces of the King,
他的劍是不會失手的
he could not have missed.
所以  只有一個解釋
There is only one explanation,
是他自己願意放棄
he must have abandoned the mission.
你到底跟他說了什麼
What did you say to him?
我只寫了兩個字
I wrote three words.
哪兩個字
What words?
天下
"All under heaven."
你心裏只有天下
That is all you care about!
還有你
And you.
我不信
I don't believe you.
如何讓你信
How can I convince you?
拔劍
Draw your sword.
你害了無名
You've misled Nameless.
害了長空  害了趙國
You've ruined Sky and the Kingdom of Zhao.
拔劍
Draw!
當初我們相識的時候
When we first met...
你也要我拔劍
I had to prove myself to convince you.
你如何才信
What can I do this time?
我只要你拔劍
Just draw your sword!
你為什麼不擋我的劍
Why didn't you fend off my sword?
這樣你就信了
So that you'd believe me.
我一直都想跟你回家
I always wanted to go home with you.
可惜不能去了
Sadly, it won't happen now.
你一個人好好保重
Take good care of yourself.
你為什麼不擋我的劍
Why didn't you defend yourself?
為什麼不擋
Why didn't you?
我們再不會浪跡江湖了
No more drifting, no more roaming.
我現在就帶你回家
I'm taking you home now.
回我們的家
Our home.
大王  殺不殺
Your Majesty, permission to execute?
大王  殺不殺  殺不殺
Permission to execute?
大王  殺不殺
Your Majesty, permission to execute?
大王  殺不殺  殺不殺
Permission to execute?
居心叵測  大膽行刺
He conspired to assassinate Your Majesty.
殺無赦
Show no mercy!
這是大王制定的秦國大法
This is the law of Qin!
大王要得天下
To conquer all under heaven,
一定要令行禁止
the law must be enforced.
給世人一個榜樣
Set an example for the world!
大王  殺  大王  殺
Execute him! Execute him!
大王  殺
Execute him!
大王  殺  大王  殺
Execute him! Execute him!
大王  殺
Execute him!
殺
大風  大風  大風
Hail! hail! hail!
公元前二二一年  秦王終於征服所有六國  統一中國
In 221 B.C., the King of Qin conquered all six kingdoms and unified China.
他停止了征伐  並修建萬里長城  用以保護本國臣民免受北方族裔侵擾
He ceased all expeditions and built the Great Wall to protect his subjects from the Northern Tribes.
秦王朝成為了中國第一個王朝
The Qin Empire became the first dynasty of China...
秦始皇則是中國歷史上第一位皇帝
And Qin Shihuang... the First Emperor.